<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise shewing the liberty and bondage of the will of man, or, A treatise shewing the bondage of the will of man by nature, and the liberty thereof by grace</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2594A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355816</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1747:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise shewing the liberty and bondage of the will of man, or, A treatise shewing the bondage of the will of man by nature, and the liberty thereof by grace</title>
                  <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.B. for Anthony Nicholson in Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Moore, Senior, by Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 40 badly stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Free will and determinism --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Predestination.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110694:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE, Shewing the Liberty and Bondage of the Will of Man.</p>
            <p>Or, A TREATISE Shewing the Bondage of the Will of Man by nature and the Liberty thereof by Grace.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q>Dum Spiro Spero</q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. B.</hi> for <hi>Anthony Nicholſon</hi> in <hi>Cambridge. Anno Domini</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110694:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110694:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Chriſtian, my deſire is, that none of us that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves Chriſtians, and in that reſpect brethren; may be found walking in that evil way mentioned, <hi>Pſal. 50.19, 20.</hi> much more that we uſe not the ſame as our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to maintain our opinions, and to beat down what we fancie to be errour, for its an evil and dangerous way, and Truth needs no ſuch weapons for its defence, nor to confute errour, and ſure this can be no other than evil ſpeaking, and falſe, to give out of any that underſtand, and believe, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> by the grace of God to have tasted death for every man, and to be the propitiation for the ſins of the whole World, and the enlightner of every man that comes into the World. That they therefore exalt the nature of man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and would that man by nature hath freedom of will to that is Spiritual good: Surely this report hath riſen in the firſt raiſers of it, from ignorance of the very voyce of that Doctrine of grace, and from conceits of fooliſhneſs in the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in the plain ſayings thereof, and malice againſt ſuch as believe to ſtick cloſe to
<pb facs="tcp:110694:3"/>the ſame, and will not be waved by Philoſophy and vain deceit to prefer mens garniſhings before the plain Text: Hence ſuch envy and ſtrife, and charges of holding ſuch goodneſs in nature fallen. But whence ſuch wiſdom comes, and what accompanies it, ſee in <hi>James 3.14, 15, 16.</hi> And it is to be feared there is ſome ſecret ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifying of willing and running where they are; in this raſh cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſome to aſſert them where they are not, and ſo a putting them out of place, or elſe an overcontempt in denying their uſe where they ought to be, for ſurely the attainment of remisſion of ſins, juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, righteouſneſs, and eternal life, It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy, <hi>Rom. 9.16.</hi> For chuſing, willing, yea and running too, to attain ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to fleſhly and ſinfull luſts. I believe we all think this in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man as fallen full enough; and the end wofull alſo. But to will and run to attain the knowledge of God, and peace, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and life with him, ſurely ſuch a thing as this ſprings not from fallen nature onely, but hath ſome light, or knowledge of truth, to occaſion it, though happily abuſed, or impriſoned by ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their own wiſdom with it, <hi>Joh. 1.4, 5, 9, 10, 11. Rom. 1.18, 19, 20, 21.</hi> Yet ſuch a willing and running may be found in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral men, and how highly eſteemed ſoever by them, yet not aproved of God; <hi>Luke 16.15.</hi> as to ſay when mens willing and running is to establiſh a righteouſneſs of their own by the works of the
<pb facs="tcp:110694:3"/>Law, to get the righteouſneſs of God, <hi>Rom. 9.31, 32. &amp; 10.1, 2, 3.</hi> Or to get <hi>Chriſt</hi> and Faith in him, that they may believe He died for them, and is theirs, and they his, and ſhall have eternal life by him, if their willing and running for this, be either in and by the Traditions and Doctrines of men, <hi>Matt. 15.8, 9.</hi> Or by their own wiſdom and ſtrength from a ſelf-principle to avoid the ſecond death, and get eternal life, <hi>1 Sam. 2.9. Ezek. 4.6, 7. Joh. 1.13.</hi> All Devotions, Converſions, Reformations, and Attainments got in and by ſuch willing and running is but fleſhly and unprofitable, <hi>Joh. 3.6.</hi> and ſuch in their hopes prove either <hi>Iſmalites</hi> the ſeed of the bond-woman; or <hi>Edomites,</hi> that as profane <hi>Eſau</hi> that preferred a meſs of pottage before his birthright, or as thoſe boaſters, <hi>Pro. 30.</hi> and wandring Stars and Clouds without water <hi>Jude.</hi> And howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in words they may aſcribe this their willing and running to the grace of God, to call it the effect of his Almighty power, yet will not God justifie them in it, nor can they obtain the Righteouſneſs of God by it, or yet are they any better than natural men, what ever they profeſs, <hi>Luke 18.9, 14. 2 Cor. 10.12, 18.</hi> But I ſuppoſe this is not the willing and running that is meant in the ſtrife, but there is a willing and running that is good and approved: Commanded, <hi>Iſai 1.19.</hi> and required in all that render ſervice to God, <hi>Exod 35.5, 21. 1 Chron. 29.5.</hi> Profeſſed of the Saints. <hi>1 Cor. 9.24, 26.</hi> which is wrought in the belief of the Goſpel, <hi>Rom. 1.16. Pſ. 11.3.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:110694:4"/>in which every good endeavour is accepted, <hi>2 Cor. 8.12.</hi> and without which none come to the uſe of underſtanding, do obtain the Kingdom, <hi>Matth. 11.12.</hi> Now this willing and running, as appears in the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is ſuch as firſt is produced by the rich and free mercie of God held forth in the death of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Rom. 5.8, 10. Tit. 3.4, 5.</hi> And ſecondly, is carried on in depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God for his performance of the good he hath promiſed, <hi>Gal. 5.5.</hi> And thirdly, ſeaſoned with ſubmisſion, and patience to wait on God for his performing of his promiſes, <hi>Heb. 10.35, 36.</hi> And fourthly, exerciſed in ſuch ways and means as God himſelf hath appointed and approved, <hi>Iſai 64.5. 1 Cor. 2.9.</hi> Yet the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining is not of him that thus willeth and runneth, nor is it in the power, or for the deſert of ſuch willing and running; but of God his free gift, who freely firſt prevented by ſhewing mercy, and ſo effected the will, and in the ſeries of his goodneſs both drew and anſwered: And if willing and running were underſtood and put in their right place, it would abate the ſtrife, but I fear that Satan hath a more miſchievous deſign in raiſing the contention, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that foul Aſperſion on believers: For he knoweth how deeply he hath overthrown us; And how far we fell in our firſt Father, and how by reaſon thereof we are as we come forth from him, blinde, deaf, dead, in reſpect of Spiritual life, and favour, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God; ſo as we can neither help our ſelves out of our
<pb facs="tcp:110694:4"/>miſery, nor take hold of help though wrought for us, and tendered to us by another.</p>
            <p>And he knoweth, that the Son of God hath taken the nature of Mankinde, &amp; was in that nature made under the Law for them, and ſo died the death and wrought Redemption for them, that whoever believe in him might not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>And he knoweth that God hath immeaſurably filled <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> with ſpirit in the nature of Man, even for the rebellious, and that in certain mediums he thereby gives forth ſome Teſtimonies of his goodneſs, and in the Goſpel a full Declaration: that men might believe and ſo turn in to him.</p>
            <p>And he knoweth that God through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and for his ſake hath given to men an underſtanding above the beaſts of the earth; and ſome light, that they might diſcern and attend the means, in which his goodneſs is teſtified and his Spirit working.</p>
            <p>And he knoweth that if ſuch mediums abide unclouded and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perverted before them, and that if they according to the light gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, do in ſeeing ſee, and attend to that diſcovered in the means; The grace diſcovered would enlighten their mindes, draw their attentions, and work willingneſs and deſires in their hearts to receive, and God would convert and heal them.</p>
            <p>Therefore this enemy of Mankinde exerciſeth his malice in many wiles, to withdraw men from beholding and attending the truth, as preſented in thoſe mediums, eſpecially in the Goſpel. And this he
<pb facs="tcp:110694:5"/>doth ſometime like himſelf as an Angel of darkneſs, with preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of necesſities, or worldly honours, and riches, or perſecutions; but ſometime counterfeiting as if he were an Angel of light, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light, holineſs, and greater attainment, and for this cauſe hath his Miniſters appearing as Miniſters of righteouſneſs, to oppoſe the Teſtimony of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as ſet forth in the plain ſayings of the Goſpel, &amp; alſo in the extent of it: knowing if that be hid from men, the door of ſaving knowledge, the foundation of ſound repentance and faith, the medium to ſet their will at liberty, and make free to chooſe life is hidden from them, &amp; then they are liable to be taken in his ſnares and ſeducements. But that he's miſchievous end may not be ſeen, and that he may prevail to put men by attending to ſuch plain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Goſpel, he will colour over his buſineſs with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of magnifying free and particular grace in a more excellent way, and cry down the plain Teſtimony of the Goſpel if received in the plain import of the words, as exalting the nature of Man, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing free-will thereto, to the derogation, or abating the honour of the grace of God, and ſo ſcare men from attending that in which they might meet with life; For the preventing of which miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous deſign, and removing that falſe aſperſion caſt on the truth and lovers thereof. I have writ theſe enſuing lines, which I deſire may be read, and the homelineſs of the ſtile pardoned, but the things themſelves tried and received ſo far as they appear conſonant to the Teſtimony and ſayings of the Goſpel, and no farther: The Lord in mercy ſill us with the blesſing of the Goſpel and make us of one minde therein, as prayeth the Well-willer in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: MOOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110694:5"/>
            <head>A TREATISE About the will in Man; and what freedom is in it to any thing truly good, and whence that comes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great love of God to fallen mankinde, in giving his own Son to take the nature of man, yea to be the publick man, and under the law, for, and in the room of all men; and ſo to dye for them all, that firſt and accurſed Death, in which all mankinde had elſe for ever periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And Gods being ſo well pleaſed with this Death of one for all that he hath raiſed, and exalted him, and made him Lord of all, and given them all over into his diſpoſe, and born wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him, and ſet him forth in the Goſpel to be the propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for the ſins of the whole world, that whoſoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in him, may receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and have eternal life; and that ſuch as when means are uſed towards them rebell willingly againſt him, may be juſtly judged by him.</p>
            <p>This is fully, and plainly recorded in Scripture, and declared as the ground and foundation of repentance, faith, love to God and men of preaching the Goſpel to all; of aſſerting the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of all, and of Chriſt his judging all, as is plain in the Scripture, and hath thereby been clearly proved by many.</p>
            <p>Yet by ſome, and ſuch alſo as are in eſteem both for learning
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110694:6"/>and godlineſs; this truth is not onely oppoſed with many ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties, cavils, and invention of abſurdities to faſten on it, but even the clear contrary Aſſertion affirmed, as to ſay; that God never loved all men; <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not dye for all men; he is not the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world of mankinde, calling theſe their negations Truth, and the contrary affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy Ghoſt, Error, and Hereſie, and although the beſt of them can finde but carnal weapons, as miſreporting the words they ſhould anſwer, wrong and cloudy ſtating the queſtion, multiplying queries, ſcholaſtical flouriſhes, Rhetorical chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; ſcoffings, pervertion, and wreſting of Scripture-ſayings; &amp; not one plain ſaying of the holy Ghoſt, to avouch and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance their negation withall; but ſuch expoſitions, limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and exceptions; as tend as much to deny Gods creation of all men by <hi>Chriſt</hi> his making all men righteous in the firſt publick man; that all have ſinned, that there is any cauſe for, or door of repentance for all men; That there is any real truth in the Goſpel to be preached to all men, that all men are obliged to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for any ſaving good, why they ſhould live to him, or that they ſhall all riſe and come to judgement before him, nor have they any clearer teſtimony in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for theſe or any of theſe than for that which they deny; I hope God will one day give them to ſee, &amp; ſo bring them from oppoſing to acknowledging the truth, and for that cauſe I have writ theſe few lines, if it may be to remove one of their great pretended ſtumbles, in anſwer to a groundleſs ſlander, which is this, that ſuch as believe <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> to have dyed for all men do alſo therewith hold, that men have free will by nature, and ſo magnifie the nature of man, and free will in man, Dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating thereby from the honour of the rich, and free grace of God.</p>
            <p>By what reaſon, or learning this ſhould be raiſed to be a conſequent of the belief of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his having dyed for all men,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110694:6"/>I know not, nor believe that any can ſhew, but I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to clear that part of oppoſed truth from giving any cauſe at all; or having ſo much as any ſhew for ſuch an abſurdity to be caſt upon it, and I am ſure many believing the truth are ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; And for the clearing the truth, and them, I deſire that theſe four things may be conſidered, and what the Scripture ſaith of them may be believed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The diſtinction the Scripture holdeth forth between that which <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> as the publick man, diſtinct from all other men, undertook to do, and hath done in his own perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al body with God for men, without reference to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, will, or acting of other men, and as and while they were enemies: and that which as the publick man, by virtue of that done in his own bodie, being filled with power, authority, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſpirit, he hath undertaken to do, doth, and will do, for, to, and in men, that they might know, will, act, and enjoy the virtue and bleſſing of that he hath done in his own body: The firſt of theſe being done, perfect, compleated, without the knowledge, will, or act of any other man in his undertaking, and Gods acceptance, and whether men know, and believe it, or not; yea, while they are enemies, and declared that men might know, and ſo will, act, and enjoy; and ſo demonſtrates men by nature, dead, enemies, and wanting both knowledge of, and will to any ſpiritual good before: the other to be after done and where begun, yet not compleated fully; till the viſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in glorie. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15, 19, 21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. and 3.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20, 21. and 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.1, 2. which things having largely diſcourſed into Treatiſes now publick I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear here, onely I mention this to ſhew, that the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and belief of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the free gift of God, and his death for all men, and that while enemies; and his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to receive, and ſend forth ſpirit in the Goſpel to make the ſame known, that men might diſcern, believe, will and doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110694:7"/>wholly oppoſe and deny any knowledge of, or free will in any man by nature, to that which is truly and ſpiritually good. And ſuch conceits of free will proceed from want of the right knowledge and belief of the death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for all men; And ſo I ſhall here onely enlarge in the other three things follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What will, or free will in man is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What divers conſiderations of men yet natural the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affordeth</p>
            <p n="3">3. When men are other, and more than natural, and what difference then.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The will of man, or mans will, is one of the faculties of the ſoul of a man; The ſoul, as I conceive may be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe three heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The underſtanding, or minde of a man; by which he knoweth, diſcerneth, and judgeth of things, good or bad, true or falſe, real or imaginarie, and ſo inventeth, or inferreth, all which may be called Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The will of a man, that is his bent, and inclination, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to elect and chuſe, or to reject and refuſe, with purpoſe, and reſolution, approving, or condemning according to the judgement of the minde concerning things, good, or bad.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The affections of love, joy, deſire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which in a right tempered ſoul follow the verdict of the underſtanding, and ſo the choiſe, or rejection of the will; But if the appetite, and ſenſual part get victory over the affections and ſo lead the will, the ſoul is in a diſtemper, and it is a troubleſome evil like that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.22, 23.</p>
            <p>So that without theſe three, there is not as I conceive a whole ſoul, the will being as I conceive the middle part, to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the underſtanding, and to govern the affections, that all may agree in one; now the freedom of the will is, that liberty and freeneſs it hath in it ſelf above any diſcoveries, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110694:7"/>and proffers to incline to or from, to chuſe or reject, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what the underſtanding diſcerneth, good, or bad without any force, or violence, to conſtrain it one way or other, without any neceſſitating enforcement, or band withholding; but onely as that ſeen in the object, and approved or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the judgement doth move, and ſo far is, the will free ended; and ſo the heart, and minde make free and willing; and ſuch a free, ready &amp; unconſtrained will, or willingneſs is free will indeed, and ſo far the will is free in it ſelf, and ſo account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture-language alſo <hi>Exod,</hi> 25.2. and 35.5, 21, 22.29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3, 12.</p>
            <p>Yet here is to be noted; that diſcovery of objects, giving forth of commands, and directions, layeth no conſtraint, or hindereth; but that the will of it ſelf inclining is ſtill free, and ſo accounted in the Scripture, <hi>Lev</hi> 1.3. and 19.5. and 22.19, 26. Nor doth want of power to do, or avoid, and ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh according to the purpoſe, inclination, and choice of the will, hinder the freedom of the will; But that the will may be free, and freely willing; when yet there is not power to do, or attain that which is willed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. So that freedom of will is one thing, and power of doing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and ſo let us hold cloſe to our buſineſs in minding what is free will, and in what ſenſe the will is ſaid to be free, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in things that are lawfull, or unlawfull, good or bad, that we miſtake not freedom here for liberty, or Authority given of God, for he gives none to evil, nor for power of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is another thing; But for that freedom from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, or neceſſity, In which the will, as it is a will doth, or may incline, and chuſe, or reject: more need not be ſaid of the will what it is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But now it is meet to ponder, and rightly to conceive of man according to the divers, and manifold conſiderations given us of him by the Scripture; of which I ſhall point out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110694:8"/>five conſiderations of man, as yet a natural man, and they are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As God made him in his creation of him, when he made all men in one publick man, whom alſo he made male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, and called their names <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As man by eating the forbidden fruit, in ſinning made himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As man through the propitiation made by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the ſecond publick man; hath his natural life a time preſerved, and mercies extended.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As by the virtue of the death, ſacrifice, and mediation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> man hath ſome light, underſtanding, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition given unto him, by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. As <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> doth by his Spirit, with ſome ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light, and motion, at ſome ſeaſons viſit a man, and touch his heart, ſtriving with him: and in all theſe conſiderations, we have ſeveral things to acknowledge about the will of man, and the freedom of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt conſideration, we finde God made man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, even in his ſoul according to his own Image, in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and holineſs, <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>Then was man indeed a living ſoul, and in honour, and had his underſtanding clear to diſcern the minde of God, in what appertained to man, and his will free, and at liberty in it ſelf (though by the command of God bound to the beſt) to chuſe one way, or other; and his affections ſuitable, no ſober man that I know denying; and ſo, and then man had freedom of will, to that which was natural good, and to that which was morally good, and to that which was ſpiritually good, and all had the ſame in him, as in a Root out of which they were to ſpring, and as in a publick man that ſtood in their room, elſe they could not have loſt it in his fall, and loſs.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe things that are ſince mans fall called in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110694:8"/>ſupernatural, and ſpiritual good, as the ſpiritual man; the Lord from heaven, the quickning ſpirit, life from the dead; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins through the bloud of the Son of God, enjoying his righteouſneſs, union with him, and conformity to him in death, and reſurrection, in his holineſs, priviledges, and glory, theſe things were unknown to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, nor could they ſtand, or be in that firſt eſtate he was in; theſe being no part, nor priviledge of the firſt creation, that is now old; but a new creation of things belonging to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and ſpiritual man; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. So that of theſe heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſupernatural, and ſpiritual good things, as they were not known, ſo there could be in man no will, much leſs free will to them, and ſo <hi>Adam,</hi> not having it could not looſe it, nor could we looſe ſuch free will in his fall, as we never had in him in his ſtanding; ſo that thus far I hope none will ſay, we mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the nature of man; For that freedom he had in his will, to natural, moral, and ſpiritual good, was not deſerved, nor acquired by him, but freely given, and wrought in him by God, whoſe the praiſe is; But that which is indeed freedom of will, to that which is ſupernatural, and ſpiritual good, he had not; and the knowledge of this will help to underſtand that which follows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond conſideration, as man by his abuſe of free will, did in his tranſgreſſion make himſelf; he not abiding a night in honour, became like the beaſt that periſheth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.12, 20. His ſoul was not annihilated, no more than his body, but his underſtanding, will, and affections he had ſtill; but the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God therein, the uprightneſs and holineſs thereof was loſt; and many evil inventions, found by him and us, all in him; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. Yea, he and we as far as could be in a publick one did in him become ſinfull, and guilty of death, and by virtue of Gods ſentence condemned, and in that reſpect dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 18. And by nature, and according to this conſideration,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110694:9"/>ſuch we come forth from him: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. So that all men by nature, and as conſidered in <hi>Adam,</hi> and as come forth from him, in reſpect of all we receive from him, and ſo are, and have by nature, are all ungodly ſinners, enemies to God, void of judgement in that which was truly good, and therefore deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of will, much more of freedom of will to it; yea, dead in treaſpaſſes and ſins; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9, 19 and 5.6. and 6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 2. And they that rightly believe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to have dyed for all do therein, and therewith believe all to have been thus dead; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. And therefore, in reſpect of any thing by nature, or from <hi>Adam</hi> wholly deſtitute of any freedom of will, to that which is truly good much more deſtitute of any free will, to that which is ſupernatural and ſpiritual good, which nature never had in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> nor can have but by ſome higher, and more glorious grace, than was conferred on him in his firſt eſtate; So that ſure in affirming this, is no exaltation of nature, and ſuch as talk of free will, to that is truly and ſpiritually good in men by nature, muſt have it in man thus conſidered, or not at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But here I fear ſome, that with many words cry down free will in man to good by nature, will yet be offended at me as abaſing nature too much, and object againſt me that in <hi>Rom</hi> 2.14, 15. That the Gentiles do by nature the things contained in the law; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſhew the work, or effect of the Law written in their heart; where if by nature they mean the nature of man, as from <hi>Adam;</hi> and by the work of the Law written, they mean the Law it ſelf as ſome do, and the bringing it in for ſuch an end, would argue ſuch a ſenſe to be meantt: hen and ſo to this Objection I anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though I reverence their learning and godlineſs, yet I receive not their ſenſe of this place, becauſe I finde the word nature otherwiſe uſed ſometime, than for the nature of man; and the nature of man in another conſideration alſo than
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110694:9"/>hitherto ſet forth; And I finde a great difference between the law and the work, or effect of the law in the heart; and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the words here in ſuch a ſenſe, would contradict many, plain ſayings of Scripture For thoſe that underſtand not, Do no good, are ungodly, and enemies to God, and by nature dead in treſpaſſes, and ſins, have not the holy and righteous law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their hearts; nor do freely by their own nature the things contained in the law, which if they had, and did, then had they free will indeed by nature; yea, and which is more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and power of doing alſo; and this is ſtrange, that ſuch as cry down free will in words and accuſe others to hold it, ſhould by their own interpretations in doctrine ſo highly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, and teach it.</p>
            <p>But it is clear enough, if the Apoſtles buſineſs, and ſcope from chap. 1.16. to this chap. 2.16. be well viewed, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: which was to ſet forth the goodneſs of God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Goſpel teſtimonie, and the means he uſed for men to to know it; that believing they might be juſtified and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his grace; and the equity of his proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that willingly diſobey againſt goodneſs ſo made known about making forth his knowledge; he tels us of two me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums or books; the book of creatures; God in and by natural things created, and ordered by him manifeſting his power, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and giving them in ſome meaſure to know, and calling and moving to repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. and 2.1, 2, 3, 4. and God teaching by theſe mediums; it is in reſpect of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments uſed, called the teaching of nature, or natures teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and the other is the book of Scriptures, which was not by nature, or natural mediums, but by a ſpiritual revelation from God; ſo the law to and by <hi>Moſes;</hi> and the Propheſies; and the Goſpel as now come forth; <hi>Rom</hi> 1.16, 17. which to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it comes, it brings more clear revelation of the minde of God than can be ſeen in nature, or thoſe viſible works of God in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110694:10"/>creation, and providence; and it is not the enjoyment of greater, or leſſer means, but the yeilding up thereto, according to the light therein vouchſafed, be it more, or leſs, in which goodneſs is received: again if we minde the Scripture, and man in the firſt conſideration; we ſhall finde; that man in his innocency had the Law, that is the knowledge, and love of God, and man writ in his heart; but ſinning he loſt this, and became as the beaſts in that reſpect. Yet though man loſt his uprightneſs; God and his Law loſt not his authority; man by the Law was as much obliged ſtill to know and love God and his neighbour for the grace he had conferred on him by creation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſuch the force, power, and authority of God in this Law, that it entered into the heart of man, convincing him, as bound to it, and that it was his duty to adore God, and love man; though he had neither light, nor ſtrength, nor will to either; yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what he conceived himſelf to do right, or wrong; his conſcience, or thoughts within would excuſe, or accuſe; and ſuch an effect, or work of the Law, is more, or leſs in every mans conſcience, till he by cuſtom of ſinning, and hardning his heart be ſeared, &amp; ſo paſt feeling, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. ſo that in all this is no ſuch commendation of the nature of man that he hath the Law writ in his heart, and ſo by nature doth the things of the Law, the contrary being largely teſtified in the firſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, and in the beginning of this: But now for our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what that Doing the things of the Law by that light ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by nature or natural mediums, even by ſuch as have no diſtinct revelation of <hi>Christ</hi> is, which is here ſpoken of. It is needfull that we firſt receive the Goſpel-teſtimonie; that <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for all men, and extends by virtue of his death ſome light to all, and ſo conſider man in ſome other conſideration, than as fallen in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> namely as redeemed in the ſecond, and as mercies and means are extended by and through that ſecond publick man even <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and thoſe means made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110694:10"/>effectual in him alſo by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> though for want of the Goſpel, and ſpiritual revelation he have no diſtinct knowledge of this <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> through whom he receiveth all this, and by whom he is now more accepted of God than ſuch as enjoy thoſe greater and ſpiritual means that give the diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Christ:</hi> and are not prevailed with thereby, as is to be ſeen in the example of <hi>Cornelius; Act.</hi> 10.1, 4, 31, 34, 35. And the following part of this whole chapter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. So that in all this the grace of God ſhewn in greater, or ſmaller means, by ſpiritual, or natural mediums is magnified; but the nature of man, &amp; that which of himſelf as <hi>Adams</hi> Son he willeth, and Doth, is reproved, and abaſed, as is evident throughout chapter. 1. and 2. and 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But now in the third conſideration of man, as <hi>Christ:</hi> the ſecond and publick man hath in his ſtead, and for his ſins dyed and ſo wrought a redemption, and made a peace for him; and by virtue thereof doth preſerve his life for a time, and in that time extendeth mercies and means to him that he might repent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. and ſeek him; <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.27. and live to him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. and ſo participate of the redemption &amp; peace. Here in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of man; as his ſoul, and body is preſerved in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral life by <hi>Chriſt: Pſal.</hi> 75.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>John</hi> 1.4, 5. We have ſomething elſe to conſider about the will in man, being one of the faculties of the ſoul, of the ſoul ſo preſerved: For man in the former conſideration was ſo fallen and dead, that he was ſo ſhut out, that there was no liberty to him for any good to chuſe, nor yet for evil to chuſe or refuſe; for he was neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it, and ſo his will wholly imbondaged, but now through this redemption wrought by <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and grace given by God in him, and manifeſted through him; that neceſſity of periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and impoſſibility of being ſaved; that which ſtood croſs againſt man in the mid-way between God and man, is removed, and that which held man captive is by <hi>Christ</hi> captived, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13, 16. and 4.8. and here is remiſſion of ſins, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110694:11"/>eternal life prepared for men, and given by God in <hi>Christ:</hi> that in receiving him men might receive it, and this ſet forth in the Goſpel, that men might chuſe life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38, 39. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. So that now the winter is paſt; and here is good, ſpiritual good, to be choſen, and liberty from God to chuſe the ſame; <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27, 29. but yet nature blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cannot ſee; and ſo the will is not moved nor free to chuſe this ſpiritual good, unleſs ſome ſupernatural light be given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.4, 5. but now in natural things, ſuitable to the good, and well-being of the natural life which is preſerved by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the will is alſo herein ſo preſerved by <hi>Chriſt:</hi> as there is ſome freedom in it touching natural things, and here I may ſay; the will hath as much power, or freedom to chuſe, or refuſe, as the man hath light, or underſtanding to diſcern what is good, or evil in things tending to the natural life; and this I gather from that change of expreſſion, where knowledge, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to chuſe, or refuſe are put one for another, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.4. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.16. and ſo in, and about things and actions natural, and humane, for the preſervation, ſafety and well-being of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural life, and ſuitable profits, pleaſures, and honours, with that contrary thereto; according to that which the underſtanding and minde of a man, judgeth to be good or bad, beſt or worſt, the will of the natural man is free, and doth freely chuſe, or refuſe; <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. and 11.3, 6. and 13.9, 10, 11. Although through a deluded judgement; he may be miſtaken in his choiſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 27.11, 12, 13. yea, and though he want power to attain, and do, or to avoid all that he chuſeth, or refuſeth; which may befall in this to ſpiritual men alſo, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.18. ſo that in fallen man that is yet natural, and of himſelf inclined, and imbondaged to his own ruine and harm; (he is yet through the grace of God by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo preſerved, that) there is ſuch a freedom in his will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout things natural, as is ſaid the holding of which perſwaſion attributeth nothing to the exaltation of nature, no worth, no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110694:11"/>deſert, no power for good; but abaſeth it, and magnifieth the grace, and power of God in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to ſuch weak unworthy ones, to whom in their diſtreſs he alſo ſo ſpeaketh, What wilt thou that I ſhould do unto thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.32. yet is this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of will many ways abuſed by natural men to their harm.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Some not knowing the grace of God through <hi>Christ:</hi> that dyed for them and bought them, and ſo preſerveth this freedom of will in them, as they count their tongues their own, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4. ſo their will, and this liberty, and freedom they finde in it to be of themſelves, and ſo what they attain of things they chuſe and purſue, tending to furniſh their natural life, they attribute to themſelves; and ſo ſacrifice to their own wiſdom, choiſe, endeavours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And make idols thereof, which if they knew, and believed the death of <hi>Christ,</hi> for all, with the ends and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues thereof, they would not do, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28, 2, 6, 17. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.15, 16. An evil that God warns his people to beware of, <hi>Deut</hi> 8.11, 12.14, 17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some through the ſame Ignorance, and unbelief, yet find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this liberty of will, not knowing whoſe gift it is, and to what end given, do yet in ſelf-love, and deſire of riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, chuſe that which to them apeareth the beſt; and ſo chuſe a ſober, and temperate uſe of the creatures, and a civil and modeſt behaviour in converſe with men about them, and then in a ſecret hypocriſie pretend this temperance, ſobriety, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be for God, and to him, and ſo challenge, and hope for heaven there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, agrievous, and dangerous deceit, and of as wofull an iſſue, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.12. and 16.25. and 21.2. and 30.12. And this reproved in Gods people, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.5, 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some through folly, ſetting the ſervant to rule, ſuffering their appetite, and ſenſe to command their will, do freely chuſe thoſe worſt things, and ways by which they lay Bars, and Blocks in the way of their own converſion; and ſo fore-ſtall themſelves from hearkning to better offers, when tendered; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110694:12"/>ſo provoke God to leave them to ſuch folly as is folly in the eyes of natural men; as to hire, or buy a farm before they ſee it, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18.</p>
            <p>Yet this freedom of will given by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> will ſerve to leave men that ſo abuſe it without excuſe, ſeeing they were not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to chuſe the worſt, but did it freely without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and ſuch as uſe it, but as they may; do avoid many rubs, and blocks from being in the way of their converſion; and yet in all this is no free will to that which is ſpiritually good; nor any exalting of the nature of man; but the grace of God for that freedom that is given.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But to proceed farther: to conſider man according to the fourth conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> As by virtue of the death, ſacrifice, and mediation of <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> there is by him ſome light, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and diſpoſition given into the ſoul, the minde, will, and affections of man; yea every man that cometh into the world.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this will not be believed by ſome; but is queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and denyed, it is much to produce ſome inſtances of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, where the Spirit of truth affirmeth the ſame; that it may appear unqueſtionably true, <hi>John</hi> 1.4, 5, 9. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is ſaid, to have life in him, and that life in him to be the light of men (that whence iſſues that diſcoverie of the knowledge of the goodneſs of God, and that life, mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which men have, and might further enjoy) and the light ſhineth (note it, not onely to, but) in darkneſs (in the blind underſtandings, and mindes of men, and their ways) and the darkneſs comprehendeth it not (but then it follows that more means is uſed, and then <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. He was the true light (namely from the beginning, as ſtill he is, the light of the world, <hi>John</hi> 8.12) which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and, what this light is, ſee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.27. The ſpirit of man is the candle (or lamp) of the Lord (which he hath given him, and ſet up and lighted in his heart) ſearching (and ſo diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110694:12"/>all the inward parts of the belly; &amp; this alſo is avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by good <hi>Elihu, Job.</hi> 32.8. there is a ſpirit in man, and the in ſpiration of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding and that this ſpirit, or light, and inclination, though in the ſoul, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſoul nor the body of man as from <hi>Adam,</hi> but ſome infuſion by the means of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> appeareth, in that it is ſaid to be given of God, that men by it might inquire after, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the goodneſs of God their maker, <hi>Job.</hi> 35.10, 11. and alſo that it is expreſt as a third thing diſtinct from ſoul and body, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46, 47. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. And let men call this what they pleaſe it is ſuch a light underſtanding, and diſpoſition, as in which men are ſaid to have eyes to ſee, and ears to hear, ſo as they might diſcern between that which is morally good, and morally evil, and diſcern many of the attributes of God, and much of his minde in his works, and word; yea and that teſtimony of his Son being the Saviour of the world, when it is brought to them if they cloſe not the eyes, &amp; eares given them, and refuſe to uſe them to the end for which they were given them and that is it they are reproved for, as is clear <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 28, 27 <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. And hereby it is; that many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men have ſo diſcerned, the being and attributes of God, in his works, and have been ſo inclined to many moral good things, and diſapproved moral evils; which though ſome of good eſteem calls the Reliques of Gods Image left in <hi>Adam</hi> after the fall, and therein unwittingly magnifie nature; and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſome light and freedom of will to it, and deny man to be dead in ſin by the fall: yet the truth is, thoſe things are the fruit of that life in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for men, and by him given in to them, <hi>John.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>So that as man is thus conſidered he hath from <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuch light or ſpirit, as if heeded, and ſuffered would make his will free to moral good things, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.5, 21, 26. So as in this reſpect, there is given by <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo much freedom as the will is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110694:13"/>but might chuſe the beſt, in reſpect of moral good, or evil preſented unto it and in reſpect of attending to, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the Goſpel, which attended to, would work a better freedom, whence in their not ſo chuſing, they are charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (not with a neceſſitous turning aſide, but) to have choſen their own ways, and that which God delighted not in, and 65.12. and 66.3, 4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29, 31. And all this is no affirmation of free will in man by nature to that which is ſupernaturally, and ſpiritually good; for that it yet is not, nor of it ſelf can be, without ſome farther grace than here mentioned, though in right uſe of this ſhewn, even that might be met withall, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.32, 36. But this ſerveth ſtill, to abaſe mans nature as fallen, and to magnifie the grace of God in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and to aggravate the finfulneſs of evil chuſers of their own ways; yet this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of will, though graciouſly given by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to men for their good, is by many divers ways abuſed to their greater harm, for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some even when God appears, and the knowledge of God is tendered, and they diſcern the ſame, right, and good, and might chuſe to behold the light, and attend the means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge tendered, in which they ſhould meet with bleſſing; yet becauſe it reproveth, and calleth off from ſome Idolatry, or uncleanneſs, or worldly luſts, which they exceedingly love; they without conſtraint do freely refuſe, to hearken to ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and yield to ſuch acts of worſhip, and juſtice, mercy and ſobriety, as would hinder the ſatisfying of thoſe luſts, and as freely chuſe the contrary which they might have refuſed, but would not, and in this their evil choiſe, they ſay to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, Depart from us we will not the knowledge of thy ways; whence theſe are ſaid, to be the wicked indeed, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 4. <hi>Job.</hi> 21.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some when light and truth is extended, diſcovering the vanity of Idols, and falſe worſhip, and mens doctrines and ways, and the goodneſs of truth, ſo as they begin to ſee what is right,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110694:13"/>and good, and like it, as good to be followed; yet becauſe they love peace to the fleſh, and the approbation of man in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and in fame for learning, and devotion; they not by any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity or conſtraint, but willingly ſtick to their commands and doctrines, and refuſe to embrace the truth, that would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger to their diſpleaſure and reproach, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.3, 4, 9, 11. <hi>John</hi> 5.44. and 12.42, 43. whence that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12, 13. Neither will this <hi>Plea</hi> help them, or be found true; their wills were ſo chained, they could not chuſe to accept the better part in this; they were for want of liberty, and freedom of will neceſſitated to chuſe the worſe part herein, and whoever help them with this <hi>Plea,</hi> God will reprove it, <hi>Iſai</hi> 5.1, 4. <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some there are, that for want of the right knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> having dyed for all, and the ends, and virtues of his death ſtoop not to come in at that door, wherein they will be found no better than others, and chuſe not that efficacie of the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they might be quickned by him; yet make ſome uſe though a wrong one of this liberty, and freedom of will given them by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that is this; that being convinced of ſin, and their guiltineſs of it by the Law, and the wages to be death, and ſo terrified by the Law, with the apprehenſions of Gods anger and judgement, and ſo of hell, and believing the Law to be holy, juſt, and good, as indeed it is; they ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Law, and chuſe to work ſorrow on their hearts for their ſins, and ſo to leave them, and to learn the knowledge of thoſe righteous affections, and ſervices commanded by the Law hereby to get the righteouſneſs of God, and as by uſe, and cuſtom, they attain to ſome inward frames, and prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in duties; they would from thence conclude themſelves alive to God, but finding wants, they will look to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as one that dyed for ſuch; that ſo what is wanting in them, may be made up by him; and being come to this, they truſt, there are <hi>Chriſts;</hi> they have faith, they are righteous, and have ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110694:14"/>free-will to that which is ſupernatural and ſpiritual good, but in this they are not wiſe, but farther off &amp; unjuſtified ſtill, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. and 9.33. and 10.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Job</hi> 9.30, 33. And yet in this is ſomething that is worſe; for they yet not knowing that which is indeed ſupernatural and ſpiritual good, and ſo having as yet no freedom of will to chuſe that. But onely this freedom forementioned to that is morally good, and all the zeal, and exerciſe being an act of their will though help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that freedom in it given by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to men; yet this now they call, an act of ſupernatural grace, and ſay, it is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun freedom of will to that which is ſpiritually good; and that it was wrought in them by the free grace and the almighty, and unreſiſtable power of God, without which they ſay, they could not have had it. And they acknowledge it, the work of his grace, as did the Phariſee; <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. And of this act, and fruit of their will, they make a great Idol, and myſteriouſly worſhip it, for from hence they fetch their knowledge, and on this they build their faith and hope, that they are elect, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for them; that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is theirs, and they his, that the promiſes belong to them and that they ſhall have eternal life, and can never fall away; &amp; though they think and to others ſay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is their foundation, yet the truth is, the firſt and bottom matter is the foundation, and that to them is this act pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by their will, without which they know not whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for them or no; ſo that they build that perſwaſion hereon alſo; and hence is their aſſurance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> raiſed; though every whit as much deceived as they, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. And as high-thoughted of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.13. <hi>Iſai</hi> 65.5.</p>
            <p>Yet do they blinde themſeves and others from diſcerning this, by earneſt, and zealous crying down all free-will in man to any ſuch good as they have, as if there be any, it muſt needs be by nature; and ſo as perſuing others as magnifiers of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110694:14"/>and holding man hath free-will to that is ſpiritually good, therefore you may be ſure they are far from any ſuch thing: and yet all this while, they have no more but that freedom of will that is by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> given to all men, though not ſo to work with, and build on, the Lord help ſuch as are ſnared with it out of this myſterious Deceit, that they may not be as thoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.12, 13. or he, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. Lamentable it is, that ſo good, and gracious a gift given to man, ſhould be ſo abuſed, but it will leave at laſt the abuſers excuſeleſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But I will now add, the laſt conſideration of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man, and that is as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> by the virtue of his death, ſacrifice, and mediation, doth by his ſpirit in, and according to the Goſpel, viſit and move the heart with ſome ſupernatural light, and motion at ſome ſeaſons ſtriving with him; that there are ſuch ſeaſons of gracious viſitations, and eſpecially where the Goſpel is plainly preached (&amp; I need not in our Nation ſtretch my Aſſertion any farther) is evident; for the plain preaching of the Goſpel is it ſelf a gracious viſitation to a people, and the mean, yea the choiſe, if not the onely outward mean to enlighten mens mindes in, &amp; make their wills free to chuſe ſpiritual good things, <hi>Luke:</hi> 68, 78, 79. and 19.42, 44. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is graciouſly preſent in ſuch miniſtration of the Goſpel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1, 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. whence it is called, a miniſtration of life, ſpirit, and righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. And yet moreover at ſome ſeaſons more than others, and ſometime to one, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to another he doth more clearly, and forcibly viſit with ſome ſupernatural light and motion, diſcovering his goodneſs to the heart, and moving it with convincement and alurement, ſo ſtriving with them by his ſpirit, as appears, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 13. And in ſuch ſeaſons, he is making the will free, laying grace and life before it, moving with loving alurements, ſo as they might be free to chuſe, and have then an opportunitie to receive that freedom, yea in one ſeaſon or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110694:15"/>other, before he leave ſtriving with them; he takes off the yoke of thraldom, that there is ſo much freedom given to the will, (I ſay not that they ſhall neceſſarily, &amp; by conſtraint, but that) they might in that ſeaſon, while his preſence is ſo with them even chuſe life; yea ſpiritual good things, though many under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing it do not, as is evident, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11 4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.1, 4. I ſay not, this freedom wrought in the will of the natural man is abiding, or dwelling in him, but onely that it is given into his will at and in ſuch a ſeaſon of viſitation; and yet that this mercy of God given in ſuch ſeaſons is by many diverſly abuſed is too evident.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſome in a willing withdrawing, and turning aſide af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch knowledge, and operations of truth given; a fearfull, and dangerous evil, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.1, 4, 7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By others, though not prevailed with to receive the love of the truth, to ſave, renew, and cleanſe them yet lifting up themſelves to high conceits of themſelves as more excellent than others becauſe of ſuch viſits, ſhines, and motions, and even on that ground alſo boaſting of their enjoyments of free grace, and peculiar favour; a dangerous evil, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.13. <hi>Jude</hi> 5.6. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. the Lord give ſuch timely repentance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet laſtly that we may fully, and rightly underſtand this buſineſs, there is one thing more to be conſidered, namely, how long any is to be reckoned in the number of natural men, and that according to Scripture account is; untill, by the grace of God in <hi>Christ</hi> diſcovered, they be brought in to believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and then they are ſomething elſe, and better than meer natural men, or till for perſiſting in reſiſting this grace they be left, and ſo given up, and reprobated of God, and then they be ſomething elſe, and worſe than meer natural men; the firſt of theſe have a begun freedom of will not onely to chuſe ſpiritual good things, for that they have already, but alſo to purſue, abide in and follow after the ſame, which no meer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110694:15"/>man hath; and the latter have loſt that freedom they have before given them to moral good things, and attention to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums for ſpiritual good, being void of judgement therein: and till men become one of theſe two ſorts, they, even all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, both rich and poor, wiſe and ſimple, learned and unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in offices eccleſiaſtical or civil, and out of office, within or without the pale of the profeſt Church; Jews or Gentiles, civil or deboyſt, idolatrous, ſuperſtitious, devout or profane, and ſcoffers, meek or furious, chaſte or unchaſte, liberal or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are all of them natural, and but natural men, untill as is ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by the love, or grace of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that dyed for ſinners, diſcerned, and believed, they be brought to deny, and diſown themſelves, their own ſins, purpoſes, and ways, ſo as they believe on God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therein; accepting this grace to ſave, comfort, renew, and guide them, the bent of their heart being ſet to depend on God, to enjoy, honour, and pleaſe him; waiting on him for preſervation, and eternal life, theſe though men, and in a ſenſe natural men ſtill, <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.15. yet alſo indeed and in truth, they are ſomething elſe, more and better than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men, even the Sons of God by faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. Born of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12, 13. of water, and the ſpirit, <hi>John</hi> 3.3, 5. By the grace, and ſpirit of God, in and by <hi>Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 5.6, 8, 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. And ſo all that by the freeneſs of Gods love appearing in the death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are brought to believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo have him, by his Word, and Spirit abiding in them, and they by faith, and love abiding in him; theſe all theſe; whether babes, ſtrong men, or fathers, all are the ſons of God, members of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and in ſome degree ſpiritual, yea though by reaſon of ſome weakneſs, and oppoſitions of fleſh, and world, ſome be more carnal than ſpiritual, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2, 3. So that ſuch believers all and every one of them have not onely ſuch a freedom of will, as that they might chuſe that is good,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110694:16"/>according to their underſtanding in things natural and moral, and attention to the outward mediums for ſpiritual good things and ſo ſuch a light, or ſpirit, as God by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and for his ſake giveth to every one that cometh into the world, but they have received an oyntment from the holy One, even the word of grace, &amp; therein the ſpirit of grace into their ſpirit, and ſo have a new heart, a new ſpirit; and ſo have not onely that by which attending their will might be made free, or an opportunity in which they might have it, or ſuch a freedom onely in ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual viſit, that they might chuſe life and ſpiritual good things, but much more; for by the election grace hath made in their hearts they have choſen life and ſpiritual good things, <hi>Iſai</hi> 56.45.1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. And now have in their heart by the operation of God a begun freedom, not onely to chuſe, yea and to will, but even alſo to do ſpiritual things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. And it is behoofull, and gainfull for them to walk out in this grace as they have received, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. And in this freedom they are differenced from all natural men, and much more from them that are worſe than natural: namely,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe who by continual lifting up their own underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thinking to be wiſe, and preferring their own thoughts, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, and luſts, before the receiving, and retaining the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and teachings of God by nature or Scripture to turn at his reproof, but follow the deluſions of Satan, till they have cloſed their eyes, and ſtopped their ears, and hardened their hearts, in reſiſting the ſpirit, and blotting out the light, which God by <hi>Chriſt</hi> had given them, and ſo reſiſted the truth decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the holy Ghoſt in his viſits, and ſtrifes therein, till they be left and given up to Satan, and ſo reprobated, and given up of God: theſe, and all, and every of theſe, though in a ſenſe they be natural men ſtill; yet they are alſo ſome thing elſe, and more, and worſe than natural men, even the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> of the wicked one, the ſeed of the Serpent emphatically;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110694:16"/>the reprobate, and wicked indeed, that now cannot believe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 36. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16, 30. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5, 13. with 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18, 28. <hi>John</hi> 12.38, 40. And theſe having loſt that light they had, &amp; deſpited the ſpirit that would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them more, and for that given up of God, they are not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of all freedom of will to ſpiritual but even to moral good; and ſet with a full reſoluteneſs in their will to do the works of their father the devil, being void of all right judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>John</hi> 8.41, 44. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1 24, 28. And in this they are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced not onely from believers, but from all other men, that are reckoned in the number of natural men.</p>
            <p>And now having been ſo large in opening this buſineſs; let all this be brought together; let the will be conſidered, as one of the faculties of the ſoul; and the freedom, for a libertie (not from a command, or lawfullneſs, but) in it ſelf to chuſe the one or the other in things proffered; let the things be conſidered as diſtinct, natural, and moral, and ſpiritual; and of what, and to which is ſpoken in any affirmation: let the natural man be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as he was righteous, but is fallen in and through <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and redemption wrought for him by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſome light given him, &amp; in ſome ſeaſons liberty and opportunity for more: and let thoſe born of God be conſidered as diſtinct, and thoſe reprobated as excluded the better part. And then I am perſwaded, all that are not prejudicated through envie, and malice will confeſs that the heartie believing that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> by the grace of God did dye, and give himſelf a ranſom for all men, and that God ſo accepted this death of his for all, that he hath exalted him, and made him Lord, and Judge of all, and filled him with all fulneſs of grace and truth, to beſtow; and that if one died for all, then were all dead, and that he died for all, that thoſe that live ſhould not live to themſelves, but to him that died for them, and roſe again, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Saviour of the world, the propitiation for the ſins of the whole
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110694:17"/>world; that he is ſo diſplaied, and ſet forth in the Goſpel that all men might believe, and that ſuch as do indeed believe on him ſhall not periſh but have everlaſting life, this being the foundation of repentance and faith; the door to come in to the knowledge of God and <hi>Chriſt:</hi> the ground of the faith, and certaintie of the reſurrection of the dead, and of the equitie and certaintie of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his judging all men, and the ground and motive of true love to God and men; that this doctrine, and the belief and preaching of it, will lead no man to magnifie the nature off man as from <hi>Adam,</hi> or to think that any man hath by nature free-will to moral, or ſpiritual good; yea or that any man that is but natural hath any freedom of will to ſpiritual good things, much leſs power to attain, and do; and we that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thus proteſt againſt it.</p>
            <p>But this we believe, as we are led to in the belief of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, namely, That as <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> came into the world to ſave ſinners, and that the world might be ſaved, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.15. <hi>John</hi> 3.17. And uſeth means and ſends his Word to that end that men might ſeek him, repent, and believe, and ſo be ſaved, <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>John</hi> 1.7. and 5.24, 34. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>So he hath done that for men, and by virtue thereof doth that unto men by which in his operations they might repent and believe, and ſo be eternally ſaved; and if they be not, it is not through meer impotencie and neceſſitie, but their willfullneſs ſo far, that their deſtruction is of themſelves, not in or by the weakneſs or want of any thing done by <hi>Christ,</hi> but by their own willing diſobedience, refuſal, and evil choiſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 29, 30. and 9.12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16, 19. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. And ſo from the ſame doctrine, and theſe inſtructions of it we believe as is ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the natural life of man is by <hi>Christ,</hi> preſerved for a time that he might repent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That by <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſome means are uſed, and ſome light
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110694:17"/>vouchſafed to men for the ſame end; tending toward Salvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſome light diſpoſition or ſpirit is extended, and given into men, by which they are indued with ſome diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that may be called an eye to ſee, an ear to hear, that ſo in ſeeing and hearing they might underſtand what is naturally, and what morally good, and what of God is declared to them in his works and word about his eternal being, and God-head, his wiſdom, power, juſtice, truth, and his love, and kindneſs to man-ward, and what he hath done for them, and how he looks, and calls for their return to him, and what in mercie he ſtands readie to confer upon them in their return; according to his diſcoverie they may ſee; and with this diſcerning ſuch a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble libertie, or freedom in their will is alſo given them by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they might chuſe and ſee in ſeeing, and ſo to view and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, and chuſe to ſeek, and yield to that which is naturally, and morally good, and to attend that word, and thoſe means in which ſpiritual good things are declared and tendered to them, and in which attention to them they ſhould meet with that which would inlighen their mindes, and give ſo much freedom to their wills, as that they might chuſe that which is ſpiritually good, which yet is wanting to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by his Goſpel where it comes, and by his Spirit therein, at ſome ſeaſons, doth even lay meat before them and ſo far take off the yoke of thraldom that by his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations in ſuch ſeaſons they might chuſe life; and then is this freedom alſo given them, which becauſe they accept it not, &amp; ſo uſe it not in that ſeaſon to chuſe life as they might, it abides not in them, and ſo they cannot be ſaid to have it, but as coming in that ſeaſon, and paſſing, becauſe it was not laid hold on in that ſeaſon, and well uſed.</p>
            <p>And all this being the free gift of God by virtue of the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to unworthy men, and a fruit of his love, and kindneſs to man-ward, it magnifies not at all mans nature, as in and from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110694:18"/>
               <hi>Adam,</hi> nor affordeth any praiſe to man; but ſets forth ſtill the glory of the rich grace, and bounty of God to unworthy man, and how they are ſtill more obliged to God for this helpful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs afforded, and to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſpiritual man, by virtue of whoſe death and ſacrifice, this alſo is extended, being a fruit thereof, and it ſerves much more to abaſe corrupt and fallen man, and to aggravate his ſin and folly, that being in miſerie, and life tendered him by a Redeemer, and ſuch help given him that he might incline to hear, and attend to the means he uſeth, who would ſave him eternally, and yet men willingly to cloſe, or refuſe to uſe the eye he hath given them, and to chuſe to follow lying vanities, and ſo forſake their own mercies, rejecting the Lord of life, Oh, great ingratitude, and inexcuſable follie.</p>
            <p>As for the freedom of will in unfeigned believers; though it be but in part, yet confeſſed by us all that believe in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> I will here ſay no more to that, and for them that for willing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Spirit till they be given up of God and reprobated; that they are hardened, and totally deſtitute of any freedom of will, or poſſibilitie thereto in things truly and ſpiritually good, I ſuppoſe there is in this no difference among us that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But about natural men, not yet born from above, nor wholly overcome by Satan and ſo given up, and reprobated by God; but yet in their natural eſtate; of theſe is the queſtion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe, the queſtion is not of free-will to God by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or as we come of <hi>Adam,</hi> for that is denied by us all that believe in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> nor is the queſtion of free-will in man to things ſupernaturally and ſpiritually good; for that is denied to be in, or have any abiding in natural men, while they remain onely natural; but the queſtion is, of a freedom procured, and given into he will of man by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in which ſo much liberty is given into the will of man, that according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and tenders made in things naturally and morally
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110694:18"/>good, and the declaration of Gods love to mankinde, in his works, and in his word, the mediums to diſcover ſupernatural and ſpiritual good things when attended to, and believed; he might incline to, and chuſe to minde, attend to, and imbrace ſuch natural and moral good, and ſuch outward mediums for ſpiritual good as are ſet before him, in which is attendance to that better freedom, which in ſuch attention ſhould be met with; of this and this onely is the queſtion, and the affirmative I have teſtified to, in ſuch a ſenſe and ſo far as is affirmed in the four laſt mentioned particulars: and I ſuppoſe fully and clearly proved in the Scriptures fore-cited in the three laſt of the five conſiderations of the natural man: And yet for more ſatisfaction I will inſtance proofs more diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Proof.</hi> The Apoſtle profeſſeth that the word of faith which he preached, and that which the righteouſneſs of faith ſaith, and which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake, is the word that is nigh thee in thy mouth, and in thy heart, and that nightneſs, and being in thee, the teſtimonie of the word it ſelf: now this word which they preached was neither <hi>Adam,</hi> nor <hi>Adam</hi>-like, and natural things, nor a Law of works, but the word made fleſh, the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and remiſſion of ſins, and life in him, to be received by believing, and teſtified by confeſſion; and this word ſaith he, is not ſo far out of ſight and reach but it is very nigh thee in thy heart (that thou maieſt believe) In thy mouth that thou maieſt confeſs, as is evident; compare <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4, 10. with <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11, 15. And upon this ground, <hi>Moſes</hi> profeſſeth to have ſet life before them, and exhorts them to chuſe life, <hi>verſe.</hi> 15, 19. Surely this teſtimonie is true, in ſome plain and full ſenſe; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wreſting dominition, or addition, and it cannot hold forth leſs than what is before affirmed in the laſt four fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned particulars.</p>
            <p>To take it in ſuch a fantaſtical ſenſe as if the perſonal body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were in us, and dying, riſing and aſcending in us, is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110694:19"/>contrary to the whole teſtimonie of Scripture and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our faith, and the drift of the place it ſelf.</p>
            <p>To take Nigh and In for his ſpiritual in-being in the hearts of believers by his word and Spirit, and the riches of the myſterie in forgiveneſs, righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By and in which manner, he is in believers the hope of glorie, is againſt Scripture, which makes that peculiar to believers, and againſt the place it ſelf, which affirms this nightneſs, not becauſe, but that men might believe; Yet ſure a truth there is in the affirmation, and that in a full, and plain ſenſe, whether:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We take [in] for, for, as it will well bear and ſignifie, and is ſometime ſo uſed, yet then the firſt word Nigh implies a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for man, and made known and fit, and this implies good will to him, and ſo for him, and he ſo far made capable that he might ſo attend that he might believe, or:</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we take [In] for in, or within, as being added to Nigh, it ſeems to be taken, then we muſt take [In] for ſuch a being in as may be in an unbeliever that he might believe; and that can be no leſs than by virtue of his propitiation made, and mediation continued, extending ſuch mercie and light into men; as through him they live, and move, and have underſtanding above the beaſts; and ſo an eye to diſcern, and ſuch motion in their will, that upon his tenders of life in the means they might chuſe to behold and attend to him in them; and then though they have no power to ſave themſelves, yet he would ſave them, <hi>Iſai</hi> 45.22.</p>
            <p>And both theſe ſenſes are true, and anſwer to the words ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly, and leſs than both theſe cannot be taken, without injurie to the words: and he that denieth this preacheth not the Goſpel the Apoſtle preached, but runs at an uncertain; and this holds forth as much as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Proof.</hi> It is affirmed plainly in the Scripture, that <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> lighteth every man that cometh into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and ſo that there is a ſpirit in man, <hi>&amp;c. Prov.</hi> 20.27. <hi>Job</hi> 32.8.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110694:19"/>and 35.10, 11. and that they have eyes, and ears that they might ſee, and hear, though they refuſe in ſeeing to ſee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the wonders in the works and word of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.21. as is before ſhewn; and this is as much as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Proof.</hi> The Lord calleth upon men to look to him, to hear his voice, to underſtand, to turn at his reproof, to repent, to believe, to chuſe life, <hi>&amp;c. Iſai</hi> 42.1. and 45.22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.4, 7. and 1.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and 16.31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.15, 19. If any ſay that ſuch exhortations imply not power in the exhorted to turn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwer, I ſay not that it doth; but implies power and will in the exhorter, he being the Lord, and a capacity given by him to the exhorted, to hear and ſee, and underſtand, and ſo to attend and incline, which if they do, according to what they may by his gift, he will add more, and ſave as his word aſſures: a wicked ſervant he is that ſaith, the Lord gathers where he hath not ſown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any ſay, they ſay not God doth ſo, for he gave them power in <hi>Adam,</hi> which they have loſt, and he may juſtly require that of them he once gave them power for: I anſwer, he gave power to <hi>Adam,</hi> to as much as the Law of ten words requires; and that power he loſt; and this Law ſerves to diſcover ſin, and ſentence to death, which uſe was not for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in his innocency; and I hope ſuch as know the Goſpel, know that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will judge according to it, himſelf having been judged for us according to the Law, but the power to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſin, repent, and believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo chuſe life, that way was not in <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie, and ſo not loſt by him, and ſo as the firſt power men never had in themſelves, though in <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo this they never had in him; and if God graciouſly give not forth ſome power, in which men might look to, and receive his power, he ſhould require of men abſolute impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and then his yoke were not eaſie, but in Goſpel decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations he gives that by which men might hear; the end of his declaring &amp; calling being that men might repent and be ſaved,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110694:20"/>
               <hi>John</hi> 5.24, and 34. which will evidence as much as I have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Proof.</hi> God every way by his word, cleares himſelf from being the cauſe of mens deſtructions, either in his will or pleaſure taking in their death, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. or tempting them to evil, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. or in want of any means uſed for their good that may ſtand with his wiſdom and holineſs, and expreſſeth his heart for their coverſion, and appealeth to their conſcience, what could have been done more that he hath not done, <hi>Iſai</hi> 5.2, 6. which had been eaſily anſwered, if he had not done as much for, and in them, as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Proof.</hi> God that is mercifull, wiſe, and holy, will not look for that in his creatures for which he never gave them any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or fitneſs, or means by which it might be brought about; he would not look down from heaven upon the ſons of men to ſee if they did underſtand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If he had done nothing for them by which they might underſtand, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 4.2, 3. nor would he look for fruits if he had not done that by which fruits might have been brought forth, <hi>Iſai</hi> 5.3, 4. which could be no leſs than I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Proof.</hi> God in convincing, reproving, and condemning men as ſinners in this reſpect chargeth them neither with <hi>Adams</hi> fall, nor weakneſs, and inability in that ſenſe, but with willful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and groſs neglect or rejecting his word, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 29, 30. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. And ſaith not, they were chained in, or neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, but choſe their own ways, <hi>Iſai</hi> 66.3. And are in this fooliſh, having eyes and ſee not, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.21. which argues as much as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Proof.</hi> The convinced, that are convinced by the holy Ghoſt, ſhall experiment and acknowledge as much, when they ſhall ſee it their ſin, that they have not believed in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which could not be, if there were nothing in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him for, nor that done by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to them, by which they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110694:20"/>might have believed, <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 9. which proves as much as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Proof.</hi> The complaint or reproof of, or lamentation for the fool, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.16. wherefore is there a price put in the hand of a fool, ſeeing he hath no heart. There is a price and the price is put in his hand, and he values and loves it not, and herein he is a fool; not that he hath no eyes, or ears, or hand, and ſo cannot ſee, or hear, or receive; but that he having theſe neglects to uſe them, when ſo good occaſion is given, not that there is no price for him, or that it is far out of his reach, but the price is put in his hand, and he wants wiſdom, or a heart to ſet ſuch price on it as to part with his luſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For it is this is folly, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.3, 4, 7. And this alſo carries forth as much as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Proof.</hi> And to come to right reaſon, ſubdued to, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the word of God, this affirmed tends more to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God and the abaſement, and good of men, than that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that denieth this; let them be weighed together.</p>
            <p>That all the preſervation of mans life is by virtue of the death of <hi>Christ;</hi> and that God hath provided life for them in <hi>Christ,</hi> and that he uſeth means to bring them to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it; and that he gives them an underſtanding that they might diſcern his goodneſs in thoſe means, and that he gives ſo much freedom to them that they might incline to attend thoſe means and ſo look to him, and turn at his reproof; and that in ſo looking and turning he will give them ſupernatural and ſpiritual light, and ſave them; that they for all this, not minding his goodneſs, nor turning to him, he ſhould not onely forbear tumbling them down into deſtruction, but alſo ſtrive with more means and more force of ſpirit, ſo ſtretching forth his hand as to remove the yoke from their jaws, ſetting their will in ſome ſeaſons at ſuch liberty that they might chuſe life, and he in ſuch ſeaſons alſo laying meat before them and calling
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110694:21"/>them, what ſaith all this to us, doth it not ſay that God is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit in love, wiſdom, and mercy, to give ſuch a Saviour by whom ſuch mercie is procured? that his love, and bounty to mankinde, yea his patience, forbearance, and long ſuffering is very great? the revelation of his minde, that all might be ſaved, very true? and doth it not ſay likwiſe that God is juſt, and righteous, and his ways equal in condemning ſuch for and to whom he hath done ſo much? and they ſo willingly rebell againſt him, &amp; refuſe ſuch ſalvation; doth it not alſo ſpeak forth the truth of Gods words, that he wills not the death of the wicked that dyeth, but rather that he turn, and live? and that thoſe that periſh, do forſake their own mercies, looſe their own ſouls, and in their calamity, eat the fruit of their own ways? and for ſuch as believe; they may herein ſee all the mercies they have from firſt to laſt, the free gift of God by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and doth not this ſay like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that men were wholly loſt, corrupt, and dead, that by <hi>Chriſt</hi> a reſtoration is wrought, and mercy extended? that they are beholding to him, and his bloud and ſpirit for all the good motions that come to them? that he having ſo freely dyed for them and now doing ſo much to them; it is their own fault, and a foul, and inexcuſable fault, that they remain impenitent, unbelieving, and diſobedient? yea and ſpeaketh not this alſo for the good of man, of believers to preach the Goſpel, and therein to uſe reproofs, and exhortations, ſeeing that they may ſpeak to men in their own language, in a tongue that God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth men to underſtand? and it ſpeaks good for others to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men to hearken to the word of God, and attend to his Ordinances, and yield up to his teachings, and motions, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the light and ſtrength vouchſafed, and to watch to all opportunities, and lay hold on the ſeaſons of Gods viſitations ſeeing he is nigh to them therein, and much bleſſing to be met within them, and great danger in neglecting them: yea, yet again; this truth about ſo much grace extended by God to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110694:21"/>men, would if believed, free men from thoſe evil thoughts of God, as that his will is the prime cauſe of moſt mens deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that he ſends Goſpel, and uſeth means, and proclaims love to men, and calls them to repent, but neither intends good to them, nor gives them any power or freedom by which they might come to repentance; yea it would free them from thoſe vain excuſings of themſelves; when they neglect to hear the Word, to attend the Ordinances of God, to ſhew mercy to men, or to forbear ſuch evil courſes as they run into, by pleading, we have no power of our ſelves, and God hath given us none, and were it his will, we ſhould do theſe things, and repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He would not onely uſe outward means, and put in a motion, but overcome us with an almighty, and unreſiſtable power, and till he ſo do, we had as good ſit ſtill as ſtrive to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we are blinde, and deaf, and dead, and nothing; it is God that doth all; therefore the blame is not ours, from all which unſavorie ſtuff this truth believed would free; yea it would alſo free from the conceits of harſhneſs, and contradictions in the ſayings of the Goſpel, and from murmuring againſt God; all which the contrary opinion lead to. But I have yet heard ſome ſay, that this opinion of Gods extending ſuch grace to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral men, that they might believe, it doth magnifie ſome men as better than others, that is, ſuch as by ſuch light and means are brought in to believe, when others by the ſame were not; and to this I anſwer, that ſome are brought in by ſuch means as others are not; and that it is the fault of them which are not, and by that fault they become worſe, is true, elſe how ſhall that be righteous judgement when one ſhall be produced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another in judgement, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.15. and 11.22. and 12.41, 42. And that he that believes is better than he that did not is true, but that any betterneſs in himſelf made him a believer is falſe; but by grace, he is better in believing: this may be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated by a compariſion though all are too ſcant for ſpiritual things; ſuppoſe two men by their own folly become blinde,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110694:22"/>deaf, dumb, and ſo dead; here is both their ſin and their miſery; If one carry good things to them, to ſee, hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are both alike unworthy, and unable, but if one be helpt with ſight, hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the other not, and then both called, if he that hath his ſight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> behold not, it is his ſin; but the other, it is not his ſin, but his miſery; if both have ſight, hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> given, here is grace alike to alike unworthy, if both be called, and they heed not to ſee, hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both are faulty alike; but now if the call be continued, and greater diſcovery of good things made, and by the excellencie of the grace and riches diſovered, one be drawn to behold, and minde that he ſeeth, and heareth, and ſo come to receive thoſe free offers, and the other willingly cloſe his eyes, and ſtop his ears, and ſo refuſe, and be puniſhed, here is free grace to the one that deſerved no more than the other; yea grace more obliging him ſtill, and here is equal, and juſt puniſhment to the other, who is willingly now become worſe, ſo that man is no way exalted in this: and indeed when and whoſoever God hardens, blindes, and reprobates, he doth it equally in righteouſneſs, judicially, and juſtly, when, and after he hath given eyes, and ears, to ſee, and hear; and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the heart, and then called, and they cloſed their eyes, and ears, and hardened their hearts till God left them, as is ſhewn in opening the particulars of the truth affirmed, in all which it appears to tend to the abaſing of man by nature, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying Gods grace: But yet to clear the buſineſs, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to anſwer ſome ſcruples, and objections, that ſome think the Scripture occaſions to be made againſt it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9, 14. Eye hath not ſeen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither can he know them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is wholly and verily true, and there is nothing in the affirmation that doth ſo much as ſeem to unſay any part or word of theſe verſes, for here is not expreſt thoſe things that God hath done for the ſons of men, in creating of them righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in giving his Son to dye for them, when fallen, in promiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110694:22"/>remiſſion of ſins to ſuch as repent and believe in his Son, in calling, and uſing means: that men might repent, and believe; in ſtretching out his hand by his Spirit, working in them, that they might believe, and promiſing great happineſs to them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing; theſe are the things to be ſet before all men, and God gives them eyes that they might ſee, &amp; in diſcoverie they do ſee, though they will not ſee, that is, uſe their ſight, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.14, 15. And it is not the will of God, though the Goſpel, and grace of God, and houſe of God be ſhewn them; if they be not by that ſight, and grace ſeen, humbled, and converted; that they ſhould ſee within the excellencies of the houſe, and kingdom of God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10, 11. the Prophet muſt firſt ſhew the houſe to the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that they may be aſhamed and repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if by that ſight they be aſhamed, then ſhew them the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo our Saviour ſaith, Except a man be born of water, and the ſpirit, he cannot enter into (and ſo not ſee) the the kingdom of God in the excellencies thereof, and it is no where affirmed, that the natural man hath given him, while he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains natural, either diſcerning, or freedom of will to chuſe ſuch ſupernatural and ſpiritual things as theſe; yea the believers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of theſe, is but in a little meaſure in reſpect of what is in them, they being ſuch things as are not yet fully given to them by way of poſſeſſion, but prepared and laid up for, &amp; ſo to be waited for by thoſe that love, and wait for <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Tit</hi> 2.13. All which agreeth with, and confirmeth what I have affirmed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.4, 5. without me ye can do nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is alſo very true, and there is nothing in what I have affirmed croſs to this; for all that which is given into the minde, or will of a natural man, to fit him to attend, and yield to thoſe means <hi>Chriſt</hi> uſeth to him for good, is affirmed to be the work of his own grace; and ſo this ſaying is a caveat to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, and that they may not think to help themſelves by the mountain he hath made them; but knowing their imbecility uſe rightly what they have, to abide ſtill looking to him, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110694:23"/>waiting on him, to perfect all that concerns them, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and yielding up ſtill to his inſtructions, and motions, that ſo his word may abide in them, and they in this grace of his; ſuitable to that is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 8, 9, 10. with 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5. Though they here ſpoken to were more than meer natural men to whom yet even this caveat and inſtruction was needfull; ſo that this agreeth with that I have affirmed, &amp; inſtructeth and preſſeth to the right uſe thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A heavenly truth, and bleſſed inſtruction, and nothing in it croſſing any thing in the affirmation I have made, and ſet down: the people of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake, and for whom he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded, God had ſhewed mercie to already, ſaved them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and through the ſea, and ſet his promiſes before them of bringing them into <hi>Canaan;</hi> and they had heard his voice, ſeen his miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And God had done as much for them, as I have affirmed, done to, and in natural men, and becauſe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not believing his word, and ſetting their hearts to his wonders ſhewn, as they ought, and might; therefore God gave them not that, which I have all the way affirmed, peculiar to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, a heart to perceive, and eyes to ſee, and ears to hear the myſteries of God, that in ſpirituals they might follow him; and that <hi>Moſes</hi> that affirms the former given them, and from thence exhorts them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. and 6. and 7. and 10. Doth yet affirm this not given them of God, as yet, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.4. and that ſure not to excuſe their ſin, and lay the blame on God, but to aggravate their ſin, and rebellion to be very great, in not ſeeing and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ſaw, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Elſe ſure the mercifull God that had done ſo much for them, and promiſed ſo much to them freely, would have given them ſuch an heart before now, ſo that it was ſin, they had not that gift, even as it was the ſin of thoſe, <hi>John</hi> 16.8, 9. they had not believed, though faith be the gift of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. And thus thoſe that had received much mercy, did ſo provoke God, that he might juſtly forbear to ſhew them any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110694:23"/>farther mercy, but have conſumed them all, but yet he would not, but to whom he pleaſed of them to ſhew mercy, and be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to them he would, and who they were and are, he hath ſhewn, even them that are humbled by this his reproof, and ſo forſake their own thoughts, or purpoſes, and ways; and by the diſcoveries of his goodneſs turn to him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.1, 7, 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.7. And this to be the meaning of God, and <hi>Moſes</hi> is evident by the whole ſcope of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and this, 29. &amp; the 30. chapter, which elſe had been in vain and to no purpoſe to ſuch a people.</p>
            <p>Again note the things of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, in making uſe of that ſaying of the Lord in <hi>Moſes</hi> writings; and they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be ſupernatural and ſpiritual things, as the new birth, the birth effected by the promiſe, and ſo the appearance, efficacy, and election of grace therein: and ſo of the communication, of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, juſtification, righteouſneſs, peace, <hi>&amp;c. verſ.</hi> 8. Such as the diſcerning of, and freedom of will in chuſing is not affirmed to be in the natural man, much leſs that theſe things ſhould be in him, or of him by any natural power, or by his willing, or running to work out, or reach to himſelf, they being things to be received upon the free gift, and tender in believing.</p>
            <p>Yet again, note that he ſaith, theſe things are of God, it is in his power, love, mercy, and faithfulneſs ſtill to give, and work in us to receive; he hath not limited himſelf, nor ſet bounds to his will to hinder him from being gracious when he will, and to whom he will, that from him it may be looked for: and yet farther note, that he ſaith, that God of whom it is ſheweth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſo that he hath not yet excluded ſuch perſons as will, and run; but ſtill ſheweth mercy, gives them (who of themſelves are blinde and deaf) ſome ſight, and hearing that they might ſee, and hear, and ſo in ſeeing and hearing be convinced of the vileneſs of their ſins againſt ſo good a God, and the vanity of their own ways and ſtrifes in willing, and running, and ſo fall down before him, accepting the freeneſs of his grace receiving it to be ſaved by it; ſee an example of a receiver, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3, 7, 8, 9. and of refuſers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110694:24"/>2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. So that this place agreeth with and directeth to the right uſe of that I have affirmed to be given by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men, and is a like preſſing caveat, inſtruction and exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that mentioned, <hi>John</hi> 15.4, 5. <hi>John</hi> 6.44, 65. No man can come to me, except the father which hath ſent me draw him; except it were given unto him of my father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Surely this is altogether true, and a ſweet inſtruction, motive, and reproof; but here is nothing in it denying, or croſſing any thing I have affirmed; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I have affirmed, that it is of Gods working to draw to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as is ſeen in all ſaid.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God draweth many with the cords of a man, and bands of love, that yet do not come in to him, but draw back, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.3, 4, 7. and our Saviour ſaid not, that all that the father draweth do come to me; but every one that hath heard, (in which hearing the bands of love do faſten; and learned (that is received his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and ſo renounced himſelf and accepted of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therein choſen life) cometh to me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſaying of our Saviour is uſed as an admonition to them, becauſe of their own imbecility that cannot of themſelves come to receive his inſtruction, and lay hold on the opportunity afforded, receiving the love of the truth appearing, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bread now given them by the Father that ſent the Son, that is now calling on them, that by his grace they may believe on him, and ſo come to him, who will give them life, <hi>John</hi> 6.27, 29, 32, 33. for if he withdraw, &amp; give them up for contempt, then they cannot believe, or come, as, <hi>John</hi> 12.35, 40. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.14, 15. Suffer not the day of viſitation to paſs by unminded, take heed of being found the murmurers againſt him, as, <hi>John</hi> 6.43. leaſt that be verified, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37, 38. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, this ſaying of our Saviour is not uſed to lay the blame of their not coming upon God, but on themſelves, whoſe fault it was, <hi>John</hi> 5.34, 40. as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the like, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.4. &amp; 30.15, 16. And ſo to reprove them for not accepting his words, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110694:24"/>coming while his Father was drawing, and to ſhew the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his miniſtration to them, who had forewarned them of this; and their departure to be of themſelves, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to come in the Fathers drawing, without which he had taught them they could not come, he mindes them, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had ſaid this unto them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 65. So that this ſaying agreeth well with, and leads to the right underſtanding, and uſe of that I have affirmed like that, <hi>John</hi> 15.4, 5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. It is God that worketh in you both the will and the deed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is nothing againſt any thing I have affirmed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in that affirmed, all that is good, is ſhewn to be the free gift, and work of God by <hi>Chriſt:</hi> But the text is not as it is here aledged; nor ſo as will bear ſuch a ſenſe, but thus:</p>
            <p>For it is God that worketh in you both to will and to do of good pleaſure (or as ſome) both to will, and to accompliſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his good pleaſure, (or as others) both to will, and to do of good will, all theſe having one and the ſame ſenſe; the will being theirs, though given them of God; and the doing apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to them, though by that ſtrength given them of God, and that grace diſcovered, and given, which moveth the will to that is good, being another gift of God, and his work; and that ſtrength enabling them to do being a fruit of the ſame grace and Spirit, and ſo of God, inabling them for to do that is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually good; ſo as if they yield up to it, they have the favour and ſtrength of God going along with them to aſſiſt, bleſs, and ſafeguard them; but if they neglect and ſmother the light and motion, turning aſide, and rebell againſt him, then can they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him do nothing that is good, but reſiſting againſt God they may fear decays, and chaſtiſements; whence thoſe admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>And upon this ground the Apoſtle exhorteth them to work out their own Salvation (that which wrought within them, and this) with fear and trembling, and to do all things (this grace requireth) without murmurings, or diſputings, that they might
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110694:25"/>be blameleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that this all the way opens, confirms, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leads to the right uſe of what I have affirmed, like that in <hi>John</hi> 15.4, 5. though in this place alſo, believers, and men ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are ſpoken to who have ſome portion of the Spirit of grace and ſo ſome diſcerning of, and begun freedom in their will for, and to that which is ſpiritually good, and ſupernatural; yea, and working in them; and are directed about, and exhorted to the right uſe of that, as <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. which becauſe natural men want, therefore it is requiſit that the Goſpel which diſcovers that which will work it, if attended to, be diſcovered to them; and they exhorted according to that light and freedom God giveth them, to believe, and receive the love of the truth to ſave them, that ſo they may receive that which yet they have not.</p>
            <p>And thus have I faithfully and plainly in homely phraſes declared our perſwaſion in this buſineſs: and if in this any that love <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſeek the glory of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the good of men be otherwiſe minded: I hope wherein ſoever either of us come ſhort of the fulneſs of truth, our gracious God will reveal the ſame to us, onely whereto we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attained let us walk by the ſame rule; let us minde the ſame thing, and not judge or diſpiſe, defame, and ſlander one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. But with all humbleneſs of minde, endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and joyntly ſeek the glory of our Maſter <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and the good of thoſe he hath dyed for, and the proſperity of thoſe whom by virtue of his death he hath brought in to believe in him, which is the deſire, and ſhall be the prayer of the meaneſt and unworthieſt of that number.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Moore.</signed>
               <dateline>Whittleſee, <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
